The theme of this fall lecture Is
"I am the hope."
No one else can be your hope.
Not even God, Buddha,
Bodhisattva, the Spirit,
your husband, wife, kids, parents
can be your hope.
Only you can be your own hope.
Hence the theme of the lecture is
"I am the hope."
Before we start,
please repeat after me.
I am the hope.
I will be the hope of my life
and live a happy life.
I will be the hope of
my family and live in harmony.
our society and establish a just society.
I will be the hope of
my country and achieve a unified Korea.
I will be the hope of earth and
protect the natural environment.
Today's topic is regarding
the second one,
"I will be the hope of
my family and live in harmony."
Young people can live as they please
while they live alone.
As long as you don't do four things
- kill, harm, harass, or deceive others,
you are free to live
as you wish.
If you live in a deserted island,
there is no need to
even follow these four rules.
And yet we all live among
other human beings.
Why do we live with others
instead of living alone?
It's because it is more beneficial
for us to live with others.
The reason we live among others is
because we benefit from doing so.
The smallest unit of
a group is family.
The largest unit would be a nation,
or moreover, humanity.
We call groups that live together
to benefit from each other a 'community.'
Family is the smallest unit
of a community.
And then we have regions and
ethnicities, and then humankind.
In the past, nations were
the biggest community unit.
Nowadays we go beyond ethnicities and
nations and live within a human alliance.
We even include nature
and have created
the concept of the
'earth community.'
When we say 'human community,'
we refer to all humans on earth.
When we say 'earth community,' we
refer to all living and nonliving things.
We say it's a community
as all existences coexist
and help one another.
The world can be seen as
either 'me' or 'us.'
To be engrossed
in the thought of 'me,'
we call this asang
(self-centered delusion).
To be engrossed
in the thought of 'us,'
we call this insang (a conception
of humans being superior)
When we say 'us,'
we refer to family as the smallest,
and earth and/or humanity
as the biggest unit.
We co-inhabit with family
as living together is
more beneficial than living alone.
From a broader perspective,
it is beneficial to live together.
But from a narrower perspective, we see
conflicts of interests among one another.
We see such conflicts
even between husband and wife.
The same applies within society.
We live together because it is beneficial
for us from a broader perspective.
But if you look within, you see
conflicts between individuals,
conflicts between groups.
We also refer to such conflict of
interests as 'competition.'
When competition goes beyond
the benefit of living together,
the community collapses.
It's okay for husband and wife
to fight within not harming
the overall benefit of
living together.
But if a conflict goes beyond
the interest of being together,
the community collapses.
Even within a society, competition
between individuals should be accepted.
And yet competition should not lead to
destroying the benefit as a community.
Such competition would be wrong.
Going back, family is a community
of people living together.
There are three kinds of
relationships within a family.
The first one would be
the husband and wife relationship.
When two people agree to live together,
a relationship is formed.
Once such a relationship is formed,
there are certain things that follow.
You need to consider your husband's
parents/wife's parents as your own.
And yet this is rather difficult
to do in reality.
It's as if you have
a new set of parents.
Not only do you get
a new husband or wife,
but you automatically get
a new set of parents.
It's not easy adjusting to
a new husband/wife,
nor is it easy to adjust
to new parents.
You choose your own partner,
but your new parents are
automatically assigned to you.
While this is inevitable,
young people get married
without thinking this through.
They don't feel too concerned, even when
a new set of parents follow by default.
So the first relationship within family
is the the relationship
between husband and wife.
The second relationship is
the relationship
between you and your parents.
The third relationship is the relationship
between you and your children.
You basically create
varying relationships.
From your standpoint,
you place your partner at an equal level
while parents come before you,
and children come below you.
Hence, there are three types
of relationships.
We've looked into what we call a family
through its relationships.
When such relationships are steady,
families live in harmony.
When such relationships aren't steady,
families experience discord
and fall apart.
In that sense, we have a problem
where we need to be happy
as an individual,
but as we exist
within a family community,
the family needs to be happy
in order for you to be happy.
If the family is not harmonious,
you as an individual are not happy.
In other words, there's the aspect of
controlling your own inner peace,
while managing relationships
you have with your family members.
Husbands and wives come together
through love,
but conflict of interests follow
as well.
They have hidden agendas of hoping
to benefit from each other.
Hence, the relationship
inevitably leads to conflict.
There are two main problems
between husband and wife.
First, one being - the fact that
they have conflict of interests
as two different people.
There are also problems from
being raised in different environments.
In order to maintain a harmonious and
steady relationship in marriage,
you should first lose
the thought of benefiting from it
and think of taking loss.
And yet this is difficult
to do in reality.
Once you feel that you are taking loss
rather than gain by living together,
you end up thinking,
"I shouldn't have met him/her.
Maybe I should
consider a divorce."
Hence, you should lose the thought of
profiting through the relationship.
Instead, you should change
your mind to think,
"I should be of help to
my significant other."
You should accept your differences
and understand each other.
Dropping the idea of benefiting
from the other person is related to
teachings on greed.
Accepting and understanding
each other relates to sincerity.
Your selfishness to profit from
the other person leads to conflict.
Not empathizing and
living your life your own way
leads to conflict and anger.
Hence, it's important to drop the idea
of benefiting from the relationship,
and to accept and understand the
other person who is different from you.
These two things are
actually the foundations of love.
Simply claiming your love
is not love.
It is only real love when such
two mindsets are at the foundation.
Within your relationship
with your parents,
you should foremost know
that your spouse is present,
thanks to your spouse's
parents.
You need to acknowledge their effort
and have gratitude towards them.
You should not only be thankful
towards your own parents,
but also towards
your spouse's parents.
Within your relationship with
your children,
your children did not agree
to the relationship
like your spouse has.
You alone decided
to bring them into this world.
Hence, you should be responsible in
caring for them until they are 20.
Take good care of them
when they are little.
Be a good role model to them
as they imitate you when they are young.
In adolescence,
watch over their trials and errors
so that they can stand on
their own going forward.
Once they reach 20,
cut your emotional dependence
so that they become
independent human beings.
Let them build their own independent
family community to live in harmony with.
In old words, let them be the head of
their own household.
Separate their assets from yours.
If you can't build a good
husband and wife relationship,
or can't build a good
relationship with your parents,
or can't treat
your children properly,
families fall into conflict
and cannot live in harmony.
Then I as an individual
within the family will live in misery.
To live a happy life,
you should first be happy yourself.
Then you should build
a good relationship within family.
In summary, there are
three relationships within family.
Between husband and wife,
accept and understand your differences.
Minimize fights from
seeking personal interests.
Drop the idea of trying
to benefit from your spouse.
Try to be helpful
to your spouse.
Be thankful to your parents
as they've given birth and raised you.
Be thankful to your spouse's parents
as they've given birth
and raised your spouse.
Try and repay the debt.
If you have children,
raise them as independent individual.
In their infancy, keep them close
and care for them well.
In their youth, be a good example to them
as they learn from you.
In adolescence,
be there for them
as they prepare
to live life on their own.
Once they reach 20,
stop interfering in their lives
so that they can live
an independent life.
If you're able to build such relationships
it is better than living alone.
If you're unable to build
such good relationships,
it's better off to live alone.
Hence, you end up envying me
for living alone.
You envy me not
because I live a happy life.
You envy me for living alone
because you live an unhappy life.
Those who live alone need to put effort
into becoming happy as well.
Unhappy people who live alone don't know
the right way to live alone.
Hence, those who live alone envy
those with spouses.
Those with spouses envy
those who live alone
as they have trouble building
good relationships.
Anyone can live with a spouse
if they want to.
Anyone with a spouse can change their mind
and become single if they want to.
You can choose whichever option
you think is best for you.
But we usually don't give our best efforts
within our given circumstances.
We don't reflect on our mistakes
and think changing the situation
will make things better.
Hence, even if you divorce and
become single, you feel lonely.
Even if you marry someone,
you feel they are bothersome.
Either way,
you cannot find satisfaction.
So you hesitate
to break off the relationship,
you hesitate living together.
You hesitate because you don't want to
take responsibility for your own decision.
And yet you want to gain
all the pros of living alone,
along with pros
of living together.
You are sizing up which bowl has more rice
which has bigger beans.
You hesitate
because of your greed.
You have to take responsibility
for your choices.
If you do decide to get married,
you must understand that
it's more than just a relationship
between two individuals.
You should understand that three different
relationships occur from a marriage.
This we call a family community.
And life will be happier when you lead
a harmonious family community.